Adina Popescu: Welcome back.
In this video, we will discuss assessing stationarity and lag lengths.
Once you have estimated a VAR, EViews provides a number of useful tools
that allow you to improve the specification of the model.
As mentioned previously, EViews allows you to check the stability of the VAR
by providing the inverse roots of the characteristic AR
polynomial, both in table and graph.
The estimated VAR is stationary if all the roots lie inside the unit circle.
So from the VAR window why not go into "View, Lag Structure,"
and one has the option to select "AR Roots Table" or "Graph."
Let's select Graph.
And here we see the inverse roots of the characteristic polynomial.
And we can see that they are all inside the unit circle, including this one.
Which means that this particular VAR stationary since all roots
lie inside the unit circle.
So this is important because if the VAR is not stable,
certain results such as impulse response standard errors are not valid.
So if the solution to the characteristic polynomial has a root for l equal to 1,
then it means that either some or all of the variables in the VAR process
are integrated of order 1.
It may be also the case that the cointegration between the variables
exists.
And this instance would be better analyzed in the context of the vector error
collection model (VECM).
Let me note also that this result can be generated by the command listed here.
So also, as we discussed, another important specification in a VAR
is deciding on the number of lags in the system.
So opening up our VAR, let's note that EViews offers a number of useful tools
to investigate the lag structure of the VAR.
We can see that by going into "View, Lag Structure."
We can do a lag exclusion test or a lag lengths criteria.
Perhaps the most widely used is the lag lengths criteria.
And the lag specification box opens up, which
asks us what's the maximum number of lags for which we want to test.
There are no hard rules here, but in general if you have monthly data
you may want to set the number of lags to 12 or 24.
If you have quarterly data, four or eight.
Let us select eight.
And 1 or 2 for annual data, and then you'll click OK.
The test results are shown here.
So EViews denotes the appropriate lag lengths
for each criterion with an asterisk.
In this example, most tests seem to pick two as the appropriate lag length.
Although the Schwarz criterion would choose one, and the likelihood ratio
would choose five.
Note that if there are no exogenous variables in the VAR,
the count of the lag would start at one.
Here since we selected the constant, the lag count starts at zero.
Also note that you can replicate the results of these
tests by typing in the command window this particular command.
On the basis of these results, we would choose two
as the number of lags for the VAR.
And then we would re-estimate this VAR with just two lags.
So let me do this here.
And re-estimate the model.
And here we have it.
Notice that output now shows only two lags for each variable, as we want it.
Thanks a lot for your attention.